Harry Sternberg
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Harry Sternberg papers
1927-2000
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Sternberg, Harry
3.2 linear feet
The papers of New York City and California painter, printmaker, and teacher Harry Sternberg date from 1927 to 2000 and measure 3.2 linear feet. The collection documents Sternberg's career as an artist and art instructor through scattered biographical material, correspondence with friends, artists, collectors, curators, art organizations, universities, and galleries, writings by Sternberg and others, exhibition catalogs and announcements, news clippings, and other printed material. Also found are photographs of Sternberg and his artwork, two sketchbooks and three loose drawings by Sternberg, audio visual recordings, and one scrapbook.
Provenance
The Harry Sternberg papers were donated by Sternberg in several installments from 1967 to 2001.
Related Material
Also found in the Archives of American Art are the May Konheim papers concerning Harry Sternberg, 1934-1981, and an oral history interview of Harry Sternberg, conducted March 19, 1999, October 8, 1999, and January 7, 2000, by Sally Yard for the Archives of American Art
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Harry Sternberg (1904-2001) was a New York painter, muralist, printmaker, etcher, teacher, and political activist who relocated to California in 1957.
Harry Sternberg was born in 1904 in the Lower East Side of New York City and grew up in Brooklyn. As a child he attended his school art club where he met and became lifelong friends with artists Peter Blume and Philip Reisman. He took free Saturday art classes at the Brooklyn Museum of Art for two years and attended the Art Students League part time from 1922 to 1927 where he studied with George Bridgman. In 1926 he shared a studio with Philip Reisman where they received private instruction in etching from Harry Wickey. Sternberg began exhibiting his etchings and intermittently had drawings published in New Masses, a prominent American Marxist publication. In the late 1920s he became friends with Hudson Walker who also became a major collector of his work. In 1933 Sternberg was hired as instructor of etching, lithography, and composition at the Art Students League and continued teaching there for the next 33 years. Also around this time he became politically active in artist rights organizations, serving on the planning committee to create the American Artists' Congress and later serving as an active member of the Artists Equity Association. In 1935 he became the technical advisor of the Graphic Art Division of the Federal Art Project. From 1937 to 1939 he completed three federal mural commissions. His first mural Carrying the Mail was created for the Sellersville, Pennsylvania post office in 1937. His most famous mural Chicago: Epoch of a Great City was painted for the Lakeview post office in Chicago. It depicts the history of the city and its workers, particularly life for the workers in Chicago??s stockyards and steel mills.
During the 1940s Sternberg remained very active in arts organizations, as one of the founders of the National Serigraph Society and a member of the Committee on Art and Education in Society. In 1942 he published the first of five books on printing. Sternberg had his first retrospective in 1953 at ACA Galleries, and in 1957 he taught summer painting courses at the Idyllwild School of Music and the Arts in California. He continued teaching in the summers there from 1960 to 1967 and 1981 to 1989. Suffering from lung disease, Sternberg moved with his wife, Mary, to Escondido, California in 1966 in hopes that the climate would improve his health. In 1972 he was elected to the American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters. During the 1970s and 1980s Sternberg traveled extensively throughout the US and Mexico where he found new inspiration for his artwork. He continued teaching, exhibiting, and creating new work until his death in 2001.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of New York City and California painter, printmaker, and teacher Harry Sternberg date from 1927 to 2000 and measure 3.2 linear feet. The collection documents Sternberg's career as an artist and art instructor through scattered biographical material, correspondence with friends, artists, collectors, curators, art organizations, universities, and galleries, writings by Sternberg and others, exhibition catalogs and announcements, news clippings, and other printed material. Also found are photographs of Sternberg and his artwork, two sketchbooks and three loose drawings by Sternberg, audio visual recordings, and one scrapbook.
Biographical material includes an interview of Sternberg conducted by art curator Malcolm Warner, two ledgers documenting business activities, scattered financial and legal documents, and files regarding a few of his projects, including the film "Many Worlds of Art". Sternberg's personal and professional correspondence is with friends, artists, including Harry Wickey, Rockwell Kent, Philip Evergood, and Peter Blume, collectors and curators such as Hudson Walker and Carl Zigrosser, and art organizations, universities, and galleries.
The small number of writings by Sternberg in this collection includes drafts of articles and lectures, a manuscript for a book on etching, and notes. Writings by others consists of draft writings about Sternberg, draft exhibition catalogs, and writings by the artists Arthur Secunda and David Alfaro Siqueiros. Over one-third of this collection is printed material, including exhibition catalogs and announcements, news clippings, books written by Sternberg, school publications, and material regarding art events.
Also found are photographs of Sternberg in his studio, with students, with his wife Mary, and at the Idyllwild School. Other photographs include group photographs of Art Students League faculty as well as photographs of exhibitions, murals, and artwork. The collection also contains original artwork including two sketchbooks and three loose drawings by Sternberg and one scrapbook of news clippings and exhibition materials. Audio and video materials include several interviews of Sternberg and a video copy of his film "Many Worlds of Art".
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 8 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1927-2000 (Box 1, OV 5; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1928-2000 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1940s-2000 (Box 1, 4; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1933-2000 (Box 1-3; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Photographs, circa 1930s-1998 (Box 3, 4; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 6: Artwork, circa 1928-1980s (Box 3, OV 5; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 7: Audio Visual Material, circa 1980s-2000 (Box 3; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 8: Scrapbook, 1929-1958 (Box 4; 0.2 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Art Students League (New York, N.Y.)--Faculty; Idyllwild School and Museum for the Arts--Faculty
Subjects-Topical:
Artists' studios--Photographs; Educators--California; Educators--New York (State)--New York; Painting, American; Painters--California; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Printmakers--California; Printmakers--New York (State)--New York
Types of Materials:
Drafts (documents); Drawings; Interviews; Manuscripts; Notes; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Sound recordings; Video recordings
Names:
Blume, Peter, 1906-; Evergood, Philip, 1901-1973; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971; Secunda, Arthur; Siqueiros, David Alfaro; Walker, Hudson D. (Hudson Dean), 1907-1976; Warner, Malcolm, 1953-; Wickey, Harry; Zigrosser, Carl, 1891-
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1927-2000, Series 1:; (Box 1, OV 5; 0.3 linear feet)
  Biographical materials include career summaries and lists of his achievements, a transcript of an interview with Sternberg by art curator Malcolm Warner, and two ledgers containing price lists for etchings, sale records, dealer lists, and address lists. Other items found here include scattered financial documents and business contracts for the publishing of his books and teaching jobs. Sternberg also maintained files for certain activities he identified as "business ventures" including the design and production of Prest-Glass, a corrugated fiberglass. Also found is a file on his design and production of an easel seat, including original drawings for the design, and a file regarding the film, "The Many Worlds of Art", which he produced and directed. This file includes contracts, program notes, correspondence, and printed material about the project. Audio recordings of interviews with Sternberg are found in Series 7.
  Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
  - Career Summaries, 1960s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Transcript, Interview with Malcolm Warner, 1994, (See also audio cassettes in Series 7, Box 3) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - City Patrol Corps Discharge Certificate, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ledger, 1927-1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ledger, 1927-1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Financial Documents & Receipts, 1944-1947, 1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Business Contracts, 1941-1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - File Regarding "Business Ventures", 1932, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - File Regarding Easel Seat Design, circa 1950s, (Oversized materials also filed in OV 5) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - File Regarding the Film "The Many Worlds of Art", 1960-1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - File Regarding Committee on Art Education, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Sternberg Business Card, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Exhibition Label, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - File Regarding Easel Seat Design, circa 1950s, (From Box 1, F9) (Box OV 5)
- Correspondence, 1928-2000, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
  Sternberg's personal and professional correspondence includes correspondence with friends and fellow artists Rockwell Kent, Philip Evergood, and Peter Blume; art collector Hudson Walker; curator Carl Zigrosser, and author and friend Erle Stanley Gardner. Also found is correspondence with art organizations, art galleries and museums regarding the loan, sale, and exhibition of his artwork, and with colleges and universities regarding the exhibition of his work and teaching and lecture opportunities. Additional correspondence includes letters from former students and art scholars as well as letters of congratulations. This series also includes a large number of letters written by Sternberg to his friend William Karp, letters to Sternberg from his former teacher Harry Wickey, and holiday cards designed by Sternberg.
  General correspondence is arranged in chronological order followed by undated correspondence which is arranged in alphabetical order.
  - General Correspondence, 1932-1960 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - General Correspondence, 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - General Correspondence, 1971-1980, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
  - General Correspondence, 1981-1995, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - General Correspondence, 1997-2000 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Undated General Correspondence, circa 1932-2000 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence with William & Mina Karp, 1946-1961, 1966-1983, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 22-26)
  - Correspondence with Harry Wickey, 1928-1930, 1948-1953 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Holiday Cards, circa 1940s-1980s, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Writings, circa 1940s-2000, Series 3:; (Box 1, 4; 0.2 linear feet)
  Writings by Sternberg include draft typescripts and manuscripts for a book on etching, a draft of a lecture "Art as Skilled Activity", a guide on buying art written with Verna Small for the Artists Equity Association, and other miscellaneous drafts of essays, talks, and autobiographical writings. Writings by others include a homemade newsletter written by artist Arthur Secunda, a statement written and signed by artist and political activist David Alfaro Siqueiros, and a thesis about Sternberg's work. Among the miscellaneous writings about Sternberg is an article by gallery owner Harry Salpeter. The author of a talk entitled "The Lost Island" is unidentified, but may have been written by Sternberg.
  - Harry Sternberg, Draft Article about Poster as Art Medium, circa 1940s, (Oversized item housed in Box 4) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Harry Sternberg, Drafts of Book on Etching, circa 1949 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Harry Sternberg, "Art As Skilled Activity", 1952 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Harry Sternberg & Verna Small, "Art That Belongs to You", 1953 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Harry Sternberg, Miscellaneous Writings & Notes, circa 1940s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Arthur Secunda, "The L. A. Bugle", 2000 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - David Alfaro Siqueiros, "To All Those Who Struggled for My Liberty, With My Most Profound Acknowledgement", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Anne Suydam, Masters Thesis, "Social Consciousness in American Graphic Art and Its Reflection in the Prints of Harry Sternberg, 1929-1940", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Various Authors, Miscellaneous Writings about Harry Sternberg, 1945, 1950, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Unknown Author, "The Lost Island - A Travelogue", circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Draft Exhibition Catalog, "The Prints of Harry Sternberg", 1994 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Draft Exhibition Checklist, California Centre for the Arts Exhibition, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Harry Sternberg, Draft Article about Poster as Art Medium, circa 1940s, (From Box 1, F29) (Box 4)
- Printed Material, 1933-2000, Series 4:; (Box 1-3; 1.2 linear feet)
  There is a wide variety of printed materials, including academic catalogs and brochures, mostly from the Idyllwild School of Music and the Arts; publications from the Art Students League, such as catalogs, brochures, and newsletters; and several books written by Sternberg and others. Also found are exhibition announcements, invitations, and catalogs for exhibitions of Sternberg and others including several of his former students. News Clippings, magazines, and journals consist of articles about Sternberg, exhibitions of his work, reproductions of his artwork, and art-related events. Other items found here which document significant events during his career include newsletters, press releases, and programs.
  Folders are arranged by type of material and items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
  - Academic Catalogs & Brochures, 1967, 1981-1994 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Art Students League Publications, circa 1940-1968, 1981-1994, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 42-43)
  - Book, Harry Sternberg, Silk Screen Color Printing, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Book, Harry Sternberg, Composition: The Anatomy of Picture Making, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Book, Harry Sternberg, Realistic Abstract Art, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Book, Julian Levy, Modern Art: An Introduction, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Book, Hudson Walker, Gaul Was Divided into 3 Parts, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Book Publication Announcements, 1938, 1975, 1988, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Exhibition Announcements & Invitations, 1963-2000, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 7-10)
  - Undated Exhibition Announcements & Invitations, circa 1963-2000 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1943, 1953-1981, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1982-2000, (8 folders) (Box 2, Folder 15-22)
  - Undated Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Magazines & Journals, 1954, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Magazines & Journals, 1986-2000, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - News Clippings, 1933-1956, 1967-1989, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - News Clippings, 1990-2000, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Undated News Clippings, circa 1933-2000 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Newsletters, 1954, 1981-1998 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Press Releases, 1939-1998 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Programs, 1980, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Reproductions of Artwork, circa 1930s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, circa 1940s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Photographs, circa 1930s-1998, Series 5:; (Box 3, 4; 0.3 linear feet)
  Photographs include those which depict Harry Sternberg posing with his artwork, in his studio, at the Idyllwild School of Music and the Arts, with students, and with his wife Mary. Also found are two group photographs of faculty at the Art Students League, including Sternberg. Additional photographs are of his murals and other artwork and designs; exhibitions, including a 1949 exhibition at the Carnegie Institute and an unidentified exhibition.
  Photographs are arranged by subject.
  - Photographs of Harry Sternberg, circa 1930s-1979, 2000, (Oversized items housed in Box 4) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Photographs of Harry Sternberg in Idyllwild, California, 1958-1963 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Harry and Mary Sternberg in Escondido, California, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Group Photographs of Art Students League Instructors, 1952, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Photographs of Murals, 1930s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Photographs of Exhibitions, 1949, circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1970s-1980s, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 19-21)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Photostat Copies of Artwork, circa 1930s (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Negatives of Photographs of Artwork, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Photographs of Harry Sternberg, circa 1930s-1979, 2000, (From Box 3, F13) (Box 4)
- Artwork, circa 1928-1980s, Series 6:; (Box 3, OV 5; 0.2 linear feet)
  Artwork in this series includes two sketchbooks belonging to Sternberg. The sketchbook from circa 1928 contains sketches in pencil and ink of subway riders, including many close-ups of their faces. The second sketchbook of a later date contains annotated ink drawings of Sternberg's design ideas for art tools, furniture, and other functional objects. Also found in this series are two loose drawings of subway riders and a drawing of a tugboat all by Sternberg and a Poster depicting Sternberg created by his students for his birthday party at the Idyllwild School.
  - Sketchbook, circa 1928 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Drawings by Sternberg, circa 1930s, (Oversized, housed in OV 5) (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Birthday Poster for Sternberg, circa 1960s-1980s, (See OV 5) (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Drawings by Sternberg, circa 1930s, (See Box 3, F27) (Box OV 5)
  - Birthday Poster for Sternberg, circa 1960s-1980s, (From Box 3, F28) (Box OV 5)
- Audio Visual Material, circa 1980s-2000, Series 7:; (Box 3; 0.5 linear feet)
  This series contains audio and video recordings documenting Sternberg's career as an artist. Included are audio recordings of Sternberg's interview with art curator Malcolm Warner, and three video interviews of Sternberg conducted by the Felicita Foundation, Tony di Gesu for KUSI-TV in San Diego, and by the television program "Made in America." Also found is a videocassette copy of the film "Many Worlds of Art" directed and produced by Sternberg.
  - Sternberg Interview with Malcolm Warner, 1994, (2 sound cassettes; see also Interview Transcript, Box 1, F2) (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - "Many Worlds of Art", circa early 1980s, (1 videocassette, VHS) (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Felicita Foundation: "Touch & See" and "Harry Sternberg", circa 1980s, (1 videocassette, VHS) (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Sternberg Interview with Tony di Gesu, 1983-1984, (2 videocassettes, VHS; 2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 32-33)
  - Sternberg Interview, "Made In America: Sunday at 7",2000, (1 CD-ROM) (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Scrapbook, 1929-1958, Series 8:; (Box 4; 0.2 linear feet)
  This series consists of one disbound scrapbook containing newspaper and magazine clippings and a few exhibition printed materials documenting Harry Sternberg's career as an artist.
  - Scrapbook, 1929-1958 (Box 4)